Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף daf is ע"א, Ayin
Aleph, we're a little bit ahead and it's a short דף, daf,
so probably get even more ahead today. We pick up in the
middle of ע"א ע"א, Ayin Aleph Amud Aleph, תניא כוותיה דשמואל. Tanya
Kevatei DeShmuel. So just let's remember what we had talked about,
you know, or you know what, let's also maybe just because we
have a little extra time, let's just read from the top of
the דף. daf. Okay, I mean I won't spend a lot of
time explaining it, I did yesterday, but we'll just start from the
top of the דף daf to frame it. Okay, so again we're
dealing with the case about a father and an ארוס, arus, a
groom who did אירוסין, erusin, and the father is fundamentally the one
who annuls it, but the ארוס arus can piggyback on it and
participates in the annulment. And here we have the following משנה, mishnah,
we'll do this again from yesterday. נדרה והיא ארוסה, Nadra Vehi Arusa,
so she made this נדר neder while she was an ארוסה, arusa,
נתגרשה בו
ביום nisgaresh bo bayom and she got divorced on that day because
again, you know, from the time that somebody hears there's a 24-hour
clock for at least that person, we'll worry about the specifics later.
ונתארסה בו ביום nisarsa bo bayom and then she got, became an
ארוסה arusa again to a second guy, אפילו למאה, afilu leme'ah, even
if that happened a hundred times on the same day, אביה ובעל
האחרון מפירין נדריה, aviha uba'al ha'acharon meferin nedareha, so the father and
the last groom can be מפר, mefer, again, even though for grooms,
you know, two through one hundred, it was all a נדר neder
that she had made prior, well sometimes even for groom one it's
a נדר neder she made prior to נדר neder she made in
her father's house. And but nevertheless, since the father is the primary,
the הלכה halacha is that the ארוס arus is מפר בקודמין. mefer
bekodmin. So בעל ba'al is not, but the ארוס arus is, even
things that preceded him because fundamentally it's really the father and it
never really preceded the father, which was always under the father's control.
So therefore, even though this was made
when she was married to a different guy, and then another student
says:
"And heard in his vicinity."
Well we'll see right here whether they heard about it, they certainly
didn't say anything, they certainly weren't מקיים, mekayem, if they were מקיים
mekayem it would have ended it. Okay, but nevertheless, the father is
fundamentally the one who does it, so therefore he can always, just
the last guy can always jump on. I mean again, it does
sound strange, what do you mean, she did it when she was
married to a different guy? But you know, it's not so much
different than the fact that she did it before she got married
altogether. You came in late, you came in after the נדר, neder,
nevertheless, since you're currently the guy that is betrothed to her, you
participate with the father, okay, we need your הפרה hafara as well.
And that's true even if there was a guy that she was
married to prior. זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is the principle, כל
שלא יצאה לרשות עצמה שעה אחת, kol shelo yatza lireshut atzmah sha'ah
achat, as long as she did not gain independence for one moment,
meaning either she became a בוגרת bogeres or her father died or
there was נישואין, nisuin, any of those cases would have given her
independence. So in that case, אביה, aviha, so she's always been in
her father's house, guys have come and gone but she's always in
her father's house. So in that case,
אביה ובעל האחרון מפירין נדריה, aviha uba'al ha'acharon meferin nedareha, so it's
the father and the last guy and then because it's really the
father as we've been saying and the last guy's just piggybacked, he's
the guy now and therefore he is the guy that can do
the הפרה hafara or make a problem and do the הקמה. hakama.
Okay, let's see the גמרא. Gemara. מנלן דארוס אחרון מפר נדרים שנראו
לארוס ראשון. minalan de'arus acharon mafer nedarim sheniru le'arus rishon. Now the
גמרא Gemara is making a claim that it isn't explicit in the
משנה, mishnah, which is when the first guy died, had he already
heard of the נדר? neder? Because you could imagine that if he
heard the נדר, neder, then that might make it more his right,
you know, and so and maybe if the first guy heard the
נדר neder and died and it was actually he did have the
ability to be מפר mefer or מקיים mekayem it, maybe the last
guy's cannot jump in and take that over, right? Maybe they can
take that over if basically they're working on a blank slate, you
know, but if the first guy actually was already part of the
process, maybe the other guy can't take his place. So that's not
in the משנה, mishnah, the משנה mishnah doesn't tell you whether the
first guy heard it or not. But the גמרא Gemara sort of
assumes that he did. מנלן דארוס אחרון מפר נדרים שנראו לארוס ראשון,
minalan de'arus acharon mafer nedarim sheniru le'arus rishon, even if the first
one, they appeared to him, meaning the first one had, had the
ability to do something about them, they had been heard by as
Michael pointed out it's funny because the circumstances of נראו niru means
that they were נשמעו, nishme'u, okay they were heard by the ארוס.
arus. Anyway, how do you know that even those, a later, the
later ארוס arus now takes over? אמר שמואל דאמר קרא, amar shmuel
de'amar kra, the verse says, ואם היו תהיה לאיש, ve'im hayo tihyeh
le'ish, again היו תהיה, hayo tihyeh, the double language, which we assume
means married twice,
ונדריה עליה. unedareha aleha. So נדרים שהיו עליה כבר, nedarim she'hayu aleha
kevar, so she goes to the second תהיה tihyeh with נדרים nedarim
from the first היו, hayo, from the first ארוס. arus. Okay, so
she's carrying them over from the first ארוס arus and nevertheless the
last guy plays this role. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but
דילמא הני מילי שלא נראו לארוס ראשון, dilma hani mili shelo niru
le'arus rishon, maybe that's only if the first guy did not have
the, you know, wasn't involved in the process yet, they hadn't been
heard by him, he didn't have the ability to do anything. How
do you know the verse applies even if the first guy actually
had heard them? אבל נדרים שנראו לארוס ראשון לא מצי מפר, aval
nedarim sheniru le'arus rishon lo matzi mafer, maybe I would say that
that the second guy cannot
do, לא מצי מפר ארוס אחרון, lo matzi mafer arus acharon, the
last guy can't do. עליה קרא יתירא הוא, aleha kra yesera hu,
it says עליה, aleha, now I don't know what, ואם היו תהיה
לאיש ונדריה,
ve'im
hayo tihyeh
le'ish unedareha, it's dangling, yeah, I don't know. Anyway, but once again
the גמרא Gemara says. No, we're going to say that that's what
the first is teaching us. Okay, so again, not clear in the
משנה, mishnah, not clear in the פסוק, pasuk, but we're saying the
הלכה halacha of this משנה mishnah applies even to the case of
what do you call it? Even to the case of when the
first ארוס arus had the ability to be מיפר meifer and מקיים
mekayem and then he dies, the second one jumps in. Now, תני
כוותיה דשמואל, tani kavasei deShmuel, we taught like שמואל. Shmuel. Now, again
the... what do we mean what we taught like שמואל? Shmuel? All
שמואל Shmuel said was he quoted a פסוק. pasuk. So the ר"ן
Ran says that somehow, it doesn't sound this way from the way
it's phrased, but the ר"ן Ran says this point we just made,
that even when it's נראו לארוס ראשון, nir'u le'arus rishon, which isn't
in the משנה, mishnah, that was part of what שמואל Shmuel was
telling us. שמואל Shmuel was not just quoting a פסוק. pasuk. Somehow
the גמרא Gemara knew that שמואל's Shmuel's point of quoting the פסוק
pasuk
was more than אסמכתא.
asmachtah. No, forget whether it was אסמכתא, asmachtah, it's a דאורייתא. de'Oraisa.
But his point was not just to give a source for the
משנה, mishnah, but to also assert the framing that the גמרא Gemara
gave שמואל's Shmuel's פסוק. pasuk. To assert that the פשט pshat of
the משנה mishnah included the case where it was נראו לארוס ראשון.
nir'u le'arus rishon. Okay, when you read it, that's not what it
sounds like. It sounds like שמואל Shmuel gives a פסוק pasuk and
the גמרא Gemara makes an assertion that it's נראו לארוס ראשון. nir'u
le'arus rishon. Okay, but the ר"ן Ran says and it really sounds
this way, that the גמרא Gemara somehow understood no, that was שמואל's
Shmuel's point. שמואל's Shmuel's point was, I am going to show you
a פסוק pasuk that's going to tell you that's going to be
not only the base of the משנה, mishnah, but that's going to
also say, and I'm telling you my read of the משנה, mishnah,
says שמואל, Shmuel, is that it even applies to a case where
the ארוס... arus... where the first groom had the ability to be
מיפר. meifer. Okay, so that's seen now as the position of שמואל,
Shmuel, not the position of the גמרא, Gemara, the position of שמואל.
Shmuel. Forget the פסוק. pasuk. The position of שמואל Shmuel is that
פשט pshat in the משנה mishnah is that it applies even to
a case of נראו לארוס ראשון. nir'u le'arus rishon.
Right, now, as we say, so what the גמרא's Gemara's saying is
that, you know, that מדאורייתא mide'Oraisa so to speak, like I can
take your פסוק pasuk to just tell you if לא נראו. lo
nir'u. So שמואל's Shmuel's coming and saying even an additional point. Exactly.
So we're saying you're adding this as well.
Right. So now we're going to see is that true, even when
it's נראו לארוס ראשון. nir'u le'arus rishon. So תני כוותיה דשמואל, tani
kavasei deShmuel, we taught like שמואל. Shmuel. This is going to be
again one of these complicated ברייתות braisas where the גמרא Gemara does
very little analysis, which is why there's a huge ר"ן Ran and
somehow it's going to go ahead and prove its point. So let's
take a look.
נערה המאורסה אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה. na'arah haMe'urasah aviha veBa'alah meferin nedareha.
So you've got again this נערה המאורסה, na'arah haMe'urasah, this betrothed maiden,
her father and her husband, but we'll say the groom, annul the
vow. כיצד? keitzad? שמע אביה והיפר לה. shama aviha veHeifer lah. The
father heard and he was מיפר. meifer. ולא הספיק הבעל לשמוע עד
שמת. veLo hispik haBa'al lishmo'a ad sheMeis. This might sound familiar, very
similar to a previous ברייתא, braisa, not the same but similar. And
the husband didn't hear, the groom didn't hear until the groom dropped
dead. ונתארסה בו ביום. veNis'arsah bo baYom. And she was מאורסה me'urasah
to another guy. ואפילו מאה פעמים. ve'afilu me'ah pe'amim. Even a hundred
times. אביה ובעלה האחרון מפירין נדריה. aviha veBa'ala ha'acharon meferin nedareha. Now
if we just stopped there, it's not...
not only does it not prove like שמואל, Shmuel, it's specifically as
the case where it was לא נראו לארוס ראשון. lo nir'u le'arus
rishon. It says the guy dropped dead before he heard. Right? So
right now all we've said is the case of the משנה, mishnah,
but we've actually said it and explicitly described the case, we haven't
said what would be in the other case, but we've described this
case to be where the ארוס ראשון arus rishon did not hear
it. So far, not much of a proof to שמואל. Shmuel. Okay,
let's keep on going. שמע
בעלה והיפר לה. shama Ba'alah veHeifer lah. So the husband heard and
he was מיפר. meifer. ולא הספיק האב לשמוע עד שמת הבעל. veLo
hispik he'Av lishmo'a ad sheMeis haBa'al. And then the father didn't hear
yet and now the husband dropped dead. So you might remember this,
right? The husband hears and he is מיפר meifer and then he
drops dead. So this we've sort of something we discussed before, which
is
basically the idea that the father is the anchor, so we would
expect now that the הלכה halacha would be right that the father
can go ahead and can do the job. Yes, everybody with me,
right? Right? No, שמע בעלה ולא הספיק לשמוע עד שמת הבעל. shama
Ba'alah veLo hispik lishmo'a ad sheMeis haBa'al. The husband dies, the husband
did his הפרה hafarah and then the husband dropped dead, right? So
again, if the father drops dead, the husband can't do anything by
himself. But the husband dropped dead and he did his הפרה, hafarah,
so presumably now the father can finish it up. חוזר האב ומפר
חלקו של בעל. chozer he'Av u'meifer chelko shel Ba'al.
The father goes and now he annuls the portion of the husband.
Now, you might have said who needs him to annul the portion
of the husband? The husband did his job and let the father
just annul his portion and be done with it.
So question is whether that might be true, question is whether to
read this line literally, חלקו של בעל, chelko shel Ba'al, but it
seems like it does mean it literally and it seems like he
has to do a double הפרה. hafarah. I'm מיפר meifer in my
capacity as father, and I'm also have taken over the groom's ability
to be מיפר, meifer, I'm מיפר meifer in his capacity. And if
you remember from a day or two ago, we spoke about this
about some idea of like being מוריש, morish, bequeathing,
transferring your right to the father. The groom dies, does that ability
get transferred to the father? You might remember the whole discussion of
מיגז גייז או מיקלוש קליש, migaz gaiz o miklash kalish, does it
get... is it weak enough or to be... is it too weak
to be transferred and so on. Okay, but one way or the
other, the husband died, the father can now handle it. Okay, he's
doing his own thing. And he's doing and he's playing the groom's
role as well, again the father is the anchor. Oh, the reason
it needs another הפרה, hafarah, again, if you read this literal, מחי
חלקו של בעל meichei chelko shel baal is because the assumption is
that once the בעל baal dies, his הפרה hafarah becomes—yeah, the הפרה
hafarah dies with him. So that's actually an interesting concept. The effect
of the הפרה hafarah died with him, but because he was around
initially, somebody still has to play his role.
Okay, so therefore, play the role of the son-in-law.
Exactly. So the father steps in and plays the role, the הפרה
hafarah no longer is effective. Okay, that seems to be the mechanism
that this ברייתא braita assumes. But again, always assuming that the father
is the anchor. Now, אמר רב נתן, amar Rav Natan, still, says
nothing to do with Shmuel's point about נירו לארוס ראשון, neeru le'arus
rishon, right? Okay, אמר רב נתן, amar Rav Natan, הן הן דברי
בית שמאי. hein hein divrei Beit Shammai. These are the words of
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. You remember this from before, that בית שמאי
Beit Shammai is more
prepared—it wasn't exactly this case, it was a similar case—בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is more prepared for when the groom dies for the father
to take over. הן הן דברי בית שמאי, hein hein divrei Beit
Shammai, אבל בית הלל אומרים אין יכול להפר. aval Beit Hillel omrim
ein yachol lehafer. He cannot be מפר. meifer. Now, this might be
an idea we saw before, that somehow בית הלל Beit Hillel said—remember
the גמרא Gemara before made it about מיקח גייז, meikach gayiz, מיקלש
קלוש—that miklash kalosh maybe it had become too weak to transfer back
to the father. Okay, but here, if that were true, this would
be completely irrelevant to us because remember, right now it looks like
we're focusing on one father,
one groom, the groom died, does the father now finish it up
by himself? What does that have to do with our discussion in
the משנה Mishnah whether the last groom takes over if it were
נירו לארוס ראשון? neeru le'arus rishon?
Right. So what you have to assume the גמרא Gemara is reading
is—and that's why there's like a huge רן Ran coming up because
he's trying to work out just simple פשט pshat in the גמרא.
Gemara. Like you see huge רן, Ran, you think it's going to
be one of those complicated things trying to משיב meyashiv other סוגיות,
sugyot, no no, it's just like פשט pshat in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so anyway,
so so here's what you have to assume: that the case here
is when בית הלל Beit Hillel says that the father can't be
מפר, meifer, it means not only can the father not be מפר
meifer now that the groom has died by himself, but he also
can't be מפר meifer if—what would be another possibility?—if somebody else, another
groom stepped in. Okay, so then it's going to be—then it's going
to be our case. The groom heard it, now it's a little
bit different. There are three scenarios. One is groom didn't hear it
and died, right, that we said of course the final groom can
be מפר. meifer. The other is groom heard it, didn't do anything
and died, that was the assertion that that was פשט pshat in
our משנה, Mishnah, that that also the later groom could do it.
And the third scenario is the groom heard it, was מפר meifer
and died. Okay, what?
מקיים meikeim or מפר? meifer?
מפר. meifer. מפר. meifer. I know, it sounds like if he's מפר
meifer it should be better, but somehow that effects a מיקלש קלוש
miklash kalosh and maybe like it could make things like a little
bit caught between, you know, like fall between the chairs as they
say. So that's our scenario. So when בית הלל Beit Hillel says
אין יכול להפר, ein yachol lehafer, the assumption here means that even
if another groom steps in, the father can't do it with the
other groom. So that would be נירו לארוס ראשון, neeru le'arus rishon,
but here it's actually not going to be able, the last guy,
but it's because there was a הפרה. hafarah. So let's keep on
reading.
Wait wait, so there's two grooms, you're saying.
First guy heard it, was מפר, meifer, died. And then the second—and
when בית הלל Beit Hillel says אין יכול להפר, ein yachol lehafer,
we're saying it means even if a second groom now has stepped
in, the father can't be מפר meifer with the second groom. So
then she's stuck. She's stuck. Okay. Now that's not only נירו לארוס
ראשון, neeru le'arus rishon, it's נירו נירו לארוס ראשון neeru neeru le'arus
rishon and the ארוס ראשון arus rishon was מפר meifer it. Okay,
so במה פליגי, bemai peligi, what's the debate?
So בקל וחומר bekal vachomer if נירו neeru and he didn't do
anything—no.
No. Not that. I know, that's what you would think. במה פליגי,
bemai peligi, let's take a look. בית שמאי סברי נדרים נמי שראוי
לארוס נסרוקנא רשותו לאב, Beit Shammai savri nedarim nami sheraui le'arus nisrokna
reshuto la'av, even נדרים nedarim that were ראוי, ra'ui, I think some
have the גרסא שנירו, girsa sheniru, right? שנירו לארוס נסרוקנא רשותו לאב
ומגייז גייז, sheniru le'arus nisrokna reshuto la'av umageiz gayiz, even the vows
that were under the auspices of the first ארוס, arus, okay, it
goes back—the power goes back to the father when the ארוס arus
dies. Okay, now what מגייז גייז mageiz gayiz has to do with
any of this and how it's relevant is what part of this
like huge רן Ran tries to figure out. I'm not even going
to make an attempt. Okay, I'll just read you the first four
lines in the רן, Ran, if you look at the lines four
lines down in the רן, Ran, if you look from the top,
מגייז גייז: mageiz gayiz: לא הבנתי דברי ראשונים בזה אמאי מצי
אב לחודיה לבית שמאי דאמר מגייז גייז טעמיה דבית הלל דאמרי מיקלש
קלוש. lo hevanti divrei rishonim bezeh ammai masi av lehudei leveit Shammai
dami mageiz gayiz teimei Beit Hillel de'amri miklash kalosh. Right, what does
it have to do with מגייז גייז mageiz gayiz and מיקלש קלוש?
miklash kalosh? And he spends the entire rest of the page trying
to get some פשט pshat in the גמרא. Gemara. So you will
excuse me if I am going to just bracket the significance of
מגייז גייז mageiz gayiz right now. Okay, let's just get פשט pshat
in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
שנירו לארוס נסרוקנא רשותו לאב. sheniru le'arus nisrokna reshuto la'av. בית הלל
סברי, Beit Hillel savri, fine, that's what they hold. They hold that,
you know, the ארוס arus had the ability to do it, he
not only had the ability, he did it, he died, it transferred
back to the father. בית הלל סברי... Beit Hillel savri... אביה ובעל
האחרון מפירין נדריה, aviha uva'al ha'achron meifirin nedareha, the father and the
last guy can do it, ולא מיגז גייז, v'lo migaz gayiz, and
it's not מיגז גייז, migaz gayiz, it's not cut off. Now, again,
what? Where? Forget the מיגז גייז migaz gayiz part, okay? Where do
you get the בית הלל Beis Hillel saying that the ארוס אחרון
arus achron can do it? So the רן Ran is says that
the גמרא'ס Gemara's assumption here is, again, go figure this out. This
is why there's a huge רן, Ran, okay? But he says that
the גמרא'ס Gemara's assumption here is that for בית הלל, Beis Hillel,
the problem for the ארוס אחרון arus achron to step in is
only because the ארוס ראשון arus rishon already did it. In a
way, it's worse. He exercised his right, he did it, he was
מפר. meifer. Now, ideally you'd say he's מפר, meifer, we took care
of that. But no, as we're seeing, right, because it says that
when he dies, right, the בעל ba'al has to be מפר חלקו
של בעל, meifer chelko shel ba'al, that that act of הפרה hafara
becomes void when he dies. But because and and therefore it might
even make it harder, right, this is the irony. If he had
done nothing, he hadn't touched the נדר, neder, he just has the
potential. So fine, you just have the potential, you died, you you
fell out of the picture, that right reverted to the father, or
if another ארוס arus would stand in, the other ארוס arus would
get that right, you actually played no role so we can and
then you died, we can pretend you're not here. But then he
exercises the potential, he really positions himself as somebody who like, you
know, who plays a role in the נדר, neder, he actually exercised
that. So according to בית Beis so and then he dies. So
A, there's an assumption that when he dies, he the effect of
what he did was lost. But the fact that he asserted that
role, that's not forgotten. Okay, so there's it's still his portion still
needs needs הפרה. hafara. And now the question is, can somebody take
it over once he has staked his role as part of that
process? So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says yes, the father it can
get reverted to the father and presumably it gets reverted to the
father, it'll also go to another ארוס. arus. Yes, even though he
staked his role, his portion can be transferred. Whereas בית הלל Beis
Hillel says no, once he staked his role, nobody else can take
it over. Okay, so that's okay, that's you I think we can
understand that. Again, it is ironic that he did it and then
he died is worse than not doing it. But okay, I think
we understand. If he did it, it positioned him as, you know,
a player, okay, it got lost because he died, but he was
positioned as a player and as somebody with a stake and then
the question is can somebody else now take over that role? And
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says yes, the father can and then presumably
another groom can, and בית הלל Beis Hillel says no, once he's
positioned his role, now nobody can do it other than him and
he's dead so it's done with. But says the גמרא, Gemara, again,
now this isn't in this ברייתא, braisa, but says the גמרא Gemara
that's only because he did a הפרה. hafara. If he hadn't done
a הפרה, hafara, right, then even בית הלל Beis Hillel would say
just because he has the potential doesn't get in the way and
the father can can reclaim it and a later groom can reclaim
it. So this is all the proof according to שמואל. Shmuel. Not
much of a proof because it's asserting the whole whole עיקר ikkar
thing that we're trying to learn out isn't exactly addressed, right, but
the גמרא'ס Gemara's assuming that the whole debate is דווקא davka because
he exercised his right, yes.
Presumably both בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai would
agree that the let's say, you know, groom number one is מפר
meifer and dies or groom number one is מפר, meifer, father is
מפר, meifer, then groom number one dies. Right. Then it's מופר, mufar,
even though groom number one dies? One more
time? Father and the groom are מפר meifer and then the groom
dies.
Yeah, once it's מופר mufar it's מופר, mufar, once it's...
Does it go back? We say why would you say that it
dies back...
No, the בעל ba'al is in the middle of the process. Once
it's מופר mufar the נדר neder stops existing. Then it's gone. Alright,
so if you want to learn the רן Ran on your spare
time, I mean, the extent we have a we still have like
thirty-five minutes, but still, I don't feel it's going to be that
satisfying, but it's basically to try to figure out what the word
how מיגז גייז migaz gayiz plays any role here. Okay, I can
tell you that even going through the whole רן Ran I can't
really tell you in a clear way. And I don't think it's
just me, but maybe. Okay, anyway, back to you needed that much
פשט, pshat, but I think the basic point of how the גמרא
Gemara understands what's going on with בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי
Beis Shammai is like I said. The question being that they see
the debate דווקא davka because the groom exercised his right and did
the הפרה. hafara. Without that, it would seem to be oh, but
without that, then of course that role can be taken on by
the next guy, yes.
Whatever it's worth, my visual on this whole סוגיא sugya is like
opening a safety deposit box. You need two keys to put them
in. Right, and both guys have to...
Oh, I gave the example...
That's exactly what I said...
That's what you said. I gave the example, I don't know you
weren't here.
Put his key in the lock, but hasn't turned it.
Right, the example I gave the other time was about the nuclear
device box.
But but how does but are you trying to say how that
connects to מיגז גייז migaz gayiz or not מיגז גייז? migaz gayiz?
The key is in the slot but he hasn't turned it.
Yeah, but what does that have to do with...
He's weakened he's weakened the...
Yeah, but מיגז גייז migaz gayiz means you've cut off your part
as opposed to מיקלש קליש. miklash kalish. I don't know. I mean,
it's true that the גמרא Gemara says that when it's מיקלש קליש,
miklash kalish, it's harder to transfer your part. That seems to ultimately
be if you remember that was the assumption of גמרא Gemara before.
If you fully do your half, right, I mean if this is
like the נדר, neder, right, it's basically a... a width-wise or a
length-wise type of a thing, right? If this is the whole נדר,
Neder, do you cut it in half and I fully took away
half and a full half remains? Or do I sort of cut
it this way and it's a thinner, it's a weaker נדר, Neder,
but it's still, right? So and the גמרא Gemara somehow said that
if you weaken it, because it's weaker, it's harder to transfer, whereas
if you cut it off, it's easier somehow to transfer the other
part. So that seems to be what the גמרא Gemara and again,
בית שמאי Beis Shammai is saying it can be more transferred more
easily than according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, but more than that,
it's hard for me to directly, you know, to say too much
about this. All right, let's take a look at, yes?
מקצה גלי Mekatze Gali is to cut off, right? What? מקצה גלי
Mekatze Gali is to cut off.
Cut off, right. And מיקלש קליש Miklash Kalish is the weaker. Right.
Interesting. Right. Okay, let's take a look at the next one. The
next one is I think a little easier to get into. איבעיא
להו. Ibaia Lehu. They raised the following question: גירושין כשתיקה דמיא או
כהקמה דמיא? Gerushin k’shtika damya o k’hakama damya?
Okay, here’s a great question. I hear my... Let’s say my wife
said she took a נדר Neder and I say, all right, I’m
divorcing you, that’s it. Now, does the act of גירושין Gerushin consider
to be הקמה? Hakama? Now it could be considered to be or
it could be nothing, that’s כשתיקה. k’shtika. Okay, it could be הקמה
Hakama for one of two reasons. It could be הקמה Hakama because
the very fact that I... it could be seen that it's causal,
I'm divorcing you because of this נדר, Neder, but if I'm divorcing
you because of this נדר, Neder, it means that I'm assuming that
the נדר Neder is going to remain and that the נדר... Neder...
right? Why not just annul the נדר Neder or whatever? So on
the one hand, it shows you that I don't like the נדר,
Neder, I don't want to be married to a woman with that
נדר, Neder, but on the other hand, it shows that I want
the נדר Neder to still be around because I have another option
that I'm not doing, so the act of גירושין Gerushin implies that
the נדר Neder is still מקוים. mekuyam. Okay, that's one way of
looking at it. The easier way to look at it, but that
would assume a, that we can get into his head, and b,
that there was a causal relationship. Another way of assuming is like
I don't know, I was fine with... I hadn't made up my
mind about the נדר, Neder, but then I found out about another
piece of information that really got me upset and therefore I divorced
her. Fine. But maybe the very fact that I'm entering into a
zone where I don't have the right to do the הפרה Hafara
is an implicit הקמה, Hakama, meaning it's not that it's seen like
it's reacting to the נדר Neder and making a claim about the
נדר. Neder. It's not reacting to the נדר, Neder, but maybe the
very fact that I'm divorcing and I am sort of giving up
my right to do the הפרה Hafara is in itself considered like
an act of הקמה, Hakama, or maybe not.
Absence of action is action? What? Absence of action is action?
Well, it was an action of a גירושין. Gerushin. Okay.
But it
does show that you don't need what it... it is get... we
are getting to an important question which we have yet to address,
which is like how much is... I mean, we a little bit
dealt with it when I said you could be נישל nishal on
a הקמה, Hakama, so how much is it really נדר-like, Neder does
it need a formal verbal act? Right? If I do something that
demonstrates my will to make פירות עולם אסור עלי peiros olam assur
alay and I didn't say any words, right, it's not they're not
going to be אסור assur to me, right? So it actually is
a verbal act, that's pretty much rule number one in מסכת נדרים.
Masechet Nedarim. How much here, right, does it require a verbal act
or not? Okay, so it seems from the גמרא's Gemara הוה אמינא,
hava amina, right, that, you know, you could say, well, maybe he
does have a verbal act, הרי את מגורשת ממני, harei at megureshes
mimeni, but it's not he's not saying it, it's written, maybe that's
why, you say, but it sounds not that way, sounds like the
גמרא Gemara that maybe הקמה Hakama can be done just by a
demonstration of will even without a verbal act, and that's an important
question because we did make הקמה Hakama like a נדר Neder to
allow for a התרה hatara of הקמה.
hakama. Dying is not a verbal act.
Dying, yeah, but that wasn't an act of הקמה. Hakama. I mean,
that's effectively ends the right, to ends the powers, right?
Yeah, but it's like whatever is to divorce, so that may not
be a verbal act, but neither is dying.
Right, but dying wasn't a הקמה Hakama is all I'm saying. Dying
might impact who now has the rights to do what that guy
did. Here's the question, now so you could say well he can't
do it now that he's מגורשת, megureshes, ah no the
נפקא מינה nafka mina is... is that... well let's take a look.
Okay, okay, so let's take a look. Let's see למאי נפקא מינה.
l’mai nafka mina. But what I want to just say is the
fact that it calls it a הקמה Hakama is interesting. A, you
have to understand why like what would be the assumption of what
what it's asserting, why is it meaningful to be הקמה, Hakama, but
b, it's interesting because it would be a הקמה Hakama without a
verbal act. Okay,
so
או כהקמה דמיא? o k’hakama damya? למאי נפקא מינה? L’mai nafka mina?
What's the
נפקא מינה? nafka mina? כגון שנדרה ושמע בעלה וגרשה והחזירה ביומי. k’gon
she-nadra v’shama ba’alah v’gershah v’hachzirah b’yomei. He divorced her and then he
remarried her on the same day. Okay.
אי אמר
מר כשתיקה דמיא, i amar mar k’shtika damya, if it's like שתיקה,
shtika, מצי מפר ליה, matzi meifar leh, he can still be
מפר. meifer. ואי אמר מר כהקמה דמיא, v’i amar mar k’hakama damya,
but if it's like הקמה, Hakama, לא מצי מפר, lo matzi meifer,
he can't be מפר. meifer. Now, one important point first of all
which is who is בעלה? ba'alah? Is בעלה ba'alah case of a
נשואה? nesuah? Okay, can we put the father out of the picture?
Husband and wife are married, she makes a נדר, Neder, he divorces
her and remarries. So the ר"ן Ran says no, you know why
it can't be a case of a נשואה? nesua? Because if it
was a נשואה nesua and he divorced her and then he remarried
her, so by the second marriage that נדר neder has the status
of קודמין. kodmin. Okay? So it can only be a case
though of an ארוס. arus. Okay? So he divorced—so it's an interesting
question, right? Because it could have said, you know, why didn't you—why
do you have to ask that he remarried? No, why—well yeah, but
why don't you just say can the father now be מיפר meifer
it? The husband divorced, right? Now can the father be מיפר meifer
it? Okay? Or was that like an act of הקמה? hakama? So,
I don't know why he didn't ask that question, but that's the
question. Is it a הקמה hakama and then now he's remarried? It's
not a קודמין kodmin problem because it's an ארוס. arus. And do
we say that this completely act, which was not the words of
הפרה, hafara, but might demonstrate the—the fact that he's willing to walk
out shows that maybe he's saying he's giving up his rights and
maybe considered an act of הקמה? hakama? You wanted to ask something?
I see it more as a—as a הקמה hakama because what he's
saying is, you made the נדר, neder, keep your נדר, neder, it's
got nothing to do with me, I'm out of here.
Right.
I think it's expressing an opinion on the matter.
But either—but then would you—be—would the גמרא Gemara you think entertain the
same question? Let's just say, all right, fine. קונם פירות העולם עלי,
konam peirot ha'olam alay, right? Right. All right, I guess I'm abstaining
from buying vegetables today, you know? But then—but then he's like, "All
right, I'm abstaining from vegetables today. It doesn't mean I want you
to be מיפר meifer it." I mean, could you—could you ask the
same thing?
Yeah, that's an interesting question. You're right, that's a good question. Right?
What do we consider—I mean, here in a way what your example
was would be that it would certainly demonstrate his דעת da'at and
his assumptions, etc., but it wouldn't in a formal way change his
role. The גירושין geirushin formally changed his role. So it's better and
it's worse than your example. פירות עולם עלי, peirot olam alay, he
says, "Great, now we're going to have to eat vegetables every single
night." So you could say, "Oh look, so it demonstrated you're okay
with it because you were assuming that the נדר neder was מקיים."
mekuyam. I mean, we by the way had it before when the
woman said, הריני נזירה hareini nezira and the בעל ba'al said, ואני.
v'ani. And that's considered a הקמה. hakama. But again, that's a little
different because saying ואני v'ani directly addresses the נדר neder and uses
it and affirms it. Right? Your example is one which sort of
demonstrates his assumption that it's going to be in effect. So in
a way it's better, it directly, directly demonstrates that, as opposed to
this case. In a way it's worse because it doesn't formally play
with the mechanism of the—of the נדר neder of the נדר neder
itself. So these are all really good questions, right? Which is what
does it—what is constitutes a הקמה? hakama? How much does it—so let's
take a look at the—at where the גמרא Gemara goes.
But you think like, you know,
we're dealing with only things and all—all you have is words to
make, try, you know, and we have formalities like, "Oh, if I
said this way, this way." You know, you may think that there'd
be something formal for הקמה hakama too.
I'm trying to make this נדר. neder. You're going to be מיפר
meifer this נדר. neder. So let's keep on going. Let's take a
look.
תא שמע. ta shema. אימתי אמרו, eimatai amru, now we go to
our משנה. mishna. Okay? מת הבעל נתרוקנה רשות לאב. meit haba'al nitrokna
reshut la'av. No, not our משנה, mishna, excuse me. Is it our
משנה? mishna? Yeah no, it's a ברייתא braita we quoted earlier. Is
it our משנה? mishna? I keep on getting confused what's a משנה,
mishna, what's a ברייתא. braita. Might have been a ברייתא braita or
a משנה mishna earlier.
It's a ברייתא. braita. Okay, it's a ברייתא. braita. אימתי אמרו מת
הבעל נתרוקנה רשות לאב? eimatai amru meit haba'al nitrokna reshut la'av?
When did they say when the husband died, his powers got transferred
to the father? בזמן שלא שמע הבעל, bizman shelo shama haba'al, the
husband didn't hear. או שמע והפר, o shama v'heifer, or he heard
and he annulled. או שמע ושתק, o shama v'shatak, or he was
silent. ומת בו ביום v'meit bo bayom and he died. So as
long as he didn't do a הקמה hakama and he died, the
father can now take over. ואי אמרת גירושין כשתיקה דמי, v'ei amart
geirushin k'shtika dami,
if גירושין geirushin was like a case of not of being silent,
ליתני נמי או שמע וגירש. litni nami o shama v'geireish. Why didn't
it say that he divorced her and now the father can take
over? Right? Give the scenario of divorcing. Right? When you're talking about
the father taking over, that would have been a good scenario to
give. מדלא קתני הכא, mid'la katani hacha, since it didn't give that
scenario of the father taking over, שמע מינה גירושין כהקמה דמי, shma
mina geirushin k'hakama dami, it must be that if he—if he divorced
her, the father couldn't take over. That that would be like a
הקמה. hakama. That sounds like a pretty good proof. גמרא Gemara says,
one minute. אימא סיפא. eima seifa. No, look at the end. The
end of the ברייתא braita deals with הקמה hakama and also doesn't
give גירושין. geirushin. אבל אם שמע וקיים, aval im shama v'kiyem, if
he heard and he was מקיים mekayeim it, או שמע ושתק ומת
ביום שלאחריו, o shama v'shatak v'meit bayom shele'acharyav, or he was silent
for 24 hours and then he died. אין יכול להפר, ein yakhol
lehafer, that's he was—then it's a הקמה hakama and now the father
can't go ahead and be מיפר. meifer. ואי אמרת גירושין כהקמה דמי,
v'ei amart geirushin k'hakama dami, and if גירושין geirushin
is like הקמה, hakama, so why not give the case of גירושין
geirushin as the example where the father can't do it? ליתני ואם
שמע וגירש, litni v'im shama v'geireish, give that as an example where
also where the father can't do it. אלא מדלא קתני הכא שמע
מינה גירושין כשתיקה דמי. ela mid'la katani hacha shma mina geirushin k'shtika
dami. Let's say since it's not in the list—גירושין—it's geirushin not in
the list of—of the examples of הקמה, hakama, that proves that גירושין
geirushin should be like being silent. אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה. ela
meha leika limshma mina. Okay,
you can't prove it either way from here. This is a classic
case of the excluded middle, right? Or—I don't know middle, but the
excluded case. Right? So this is great, meaning this is the simpler
נפקא מינה nafka mina of גירושין כהקמה. geirushin k'hakama. The ארוס arus
is מגרש migaresh her, can the father now be מיפר? meifer? Or
is it too late? So the גמרא Gemara says, well we've got
this whole ברייתא braita that talks about after the ארוס arus gets
out of the picture can the father be מיפר? meifer? So the
גמרא Gemara says— but of course neither of those cases when it
says the father can be it doesn't say גירושין geirushin and when
it says the father can't be it doesn't say גירושין. geirushin. Okay
so sadly גירושין geirushin was not addressed in that ברייתא beraita but
it would have been perfect to address because it's a classic example
of the ארוס arus getting out of the picture and then the
question is can the is that a הקמה hakama can the father
now take over? אלא מדלא קתני הכי שמע מינה. Ella midelo katni
hachi shema mina. The גמרא Gemara says אלא הכא לא משמע מינה
ella hacha lo mishma mina you can't prove it from here. אי
רישא דוקא נסיב סיפא משום רישא ei reisha davka nasiv seifa mishum
reisha either the רישא reisha was דוקא davka that when it listed
the ways that the father could do it and גירושין geirushin would
have been a problem and therefore the סיפא seifa paralleled the רישא
reisha in the same cases but actually גירושין geirushin would have been
in that reading it that way that the רישא reisha was דוקא
davka גירושין geirushin would be a הקמה. hakama. Or the opposite is
סיפא דוקא. seifa davka. The סיפא seifa where it lists acts of
הקמה hakama is דוקא davka and גירושין geirushin is not an act
of הקמה hakama ונסיב רישא משום סיפא ve-nasiv reisha mishum seifa and
the רישא reisha paralleled the סיפא. seifa. Okay so you can't prove.
We have a list of הקמה hakama we have a list of
non הקמה hakama and גירושין geirushin doesn't appear in either list so
we can't prove one way or the other. Okay but this also
gives you the easiest נפקא מינא. nafka mina. The ארוס arus divorces
her, can the father now be מיפר? meifer? Okay was it an
act of הקמה? hakama? תא שמע. Ta shma. Let's go back now
let's try again with our משנה. mishna. נדרה והיא ארוסה, Nadra ve-hi
arusa, she made a נדר neder while she's an ארוסה arusa ונתגרשה.
ve-nitgarsha. Remember I don't know if you remember this our משנה mishna
talks about her getting divorced not about the guy dying right? What
about our case of our משנה? mishna? Yep. Okay. ונתארסה בו ביום
אפילו מאה אביה ובעל האחרון מפירין נדריה. Ve-nit'arsa bo bayom afilu me'ah
aviha u-ba'al ha-acharon meferin nedareha. For your question our משנה mishna has
her getting divorced and still has the father and the last ארוס
arus doing the הפרה. hafara. So שמע מינה גירושין כשתיקה דמי shema
mina geirushin keshtika dami you see it's כשתיקה keshtika דאי כהקמה דמי
מי מצי ארוס אחרון נדרי דאיכא ארוס ראשון de-ei ke-hakama dami mi
matzi arus acharon nidrei de-ika arus rishon הוקם hukam מי מצי מפר
האחרון נדרי דאיכא ארוס ראשון. mi matzi meifer ha-acharon nidrei de-ika arus
rishon. If it was a הקמה hakama how could the last ארוס
arus annul a נדר neder that the first ארוס arus was already
מקיים? mekayeim? That seems like a pretty danged good proof. So the
גמרא Gemara says no הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan
בשלא שמע ארוס ראשון be-shelo shama arus rishon not like we've been
saying according to שמואל. Shmuel. According to שמואל Shmuel you're right. Remember
according to שמואל Shmuel the whole assumption was was that the ארוס
arus heard it and it could still be transferred to the last
ארוס. arus. Okay so according to שמואל Shmuel that the ארוס arus
heard it and divorced her the act of divorce is not an
act of הפרה hafara it's not an act of הקמה. hakama. But
maybe that's not פשט pshat in the משנה mishna maybe it's not
like שמואל Shmuel maybe it's a case that the ארוס arus didn't
hear it and if he didn't hear it divorce has no meaning
okay in terms of
הקמה. hakama.
בשלא שמע ארוס ראשון.
be-shelo shama arus
rishon. אי הכי. Ei hachi. You're going to ask a dead guy
if he heard her or not?
מאי איריא בו ביום? Mai irya bo bayom? I don't know you
can ask her, it's not dead. He only divorced her.
What if he died?
I don't know. I don't know. אי הכי מאי איריא בו ביום
Ei hachi mai irya bo bayom why does it say that she
got remarried on the same day? Maybe that was part of שמואל's
Shmuel point that the ארוס arus heard it because if the ארוס
arus didn't hear it you don't have a ticking clock okay? מאי
איריא בו ביום אפילו אחר מאה ימים נמי. Mai irya bo bayom
afilu achar me'ah yamim nami. Okay so if the guy didn't hear
it why is the clock ticking? דלא שמע ארוס ושמע אב. delo
shama arus ve-shama av. Ah whose clock is ticking? Okay not the
one's biological clock okay the husband's הפרה hafara clock but it's the
father. It's the father since it's a joint process of the father
and the בעל ba'al right? So therefore the father's clock is ticking.
Now actually this raises an important question because why can't the father
do it within his 24 hours and the בעל ba'al do it
within his 24 hours? Right? So is it that either anyone of
them starts his starts the clock for both of them? Let's take
a look.
Okay אפילו אחר מאה ימים נמי afilu achar me'ah yamim nami דלא
שמע ארוס ושמע אב delo shama arus ve-shama av דבו ביום הוא
דמצי מפר de-bo bayom hu de-matzi meifer I think it means the
father can be מפר. meifer. אבל מכאן ואילך לא מצי מפר. aval
mikan va-eilach lo matzi meifer. But presumably I should double check this
but presumably then it really could work. She could get married a
hundred times over in the course of the year as long as
the father was מפר meifer his portion within his 24 hours but
presumably the בעל ba'al could do the next portion when he hears
about it no? I would think. Although hmm interesting question because here's
there's a case where no wait. The
בעל ba'al hears about it? No no no no no. If she
is not remarried if the father wants to be מפר meifer without
the last ארוס arus what then he would be being מפר meifer
his חלק chelek and the and the divorced ארוס's arus חלק chelek
right? The father heard his clock is ticking she's got married to
this guy he divorced her. If we want to say well you
do your part and the last if there's another ארוס arus he'll
do his but once he's doing his part and there's no other
ארוס arus on the scene then he's doing his part and the
dead or the divorced ארוס's arus חלק. chelek. So presumably we're setting
it up that he's waiting to do his part till he's got
the last you know till there's another ארוס arus right? So you
wouldn't have a case here when there's no other ארוס. arus. on
the scene right now you won't have a scenario where he does
his part and the other part is in abeyance. If there's no
other אריס aris on the scene he's doing both of their parts.
Okay anyway, so the point is the clock is ticking here not
because the אריס aris heard it but because the father heard it
and because we are setting up the scenario that the father and
the last אריס aris are going to do it together on the
same day. So therefore we need her to get remarried on the
same day but not because the אריס aris heard it but because
we want it to be a case in which the father and
the אריס aris are both going to be doing it. Okay,
yeah but presumably the father can do it just right now even
before they got married. Okay, right, תא
שמע tashma so we still don't have an answer because we said
our משנה mishna was not like שמואל Shmuel and therefore challenged the
whole earlier read about that whole other question or it's possible that
it's not like שמואל Shmuel and that it's when the אריס aris
didn't hear it. תא שמע tashma נדרה בו ביום nadara bo bayom
גירשה והחזירה בו ביום girsha vehachzira bo bayom okay
she made a vow that day, he divorced her and then took
her back on that day. אין יכול להפר, ein yachol lehafer, he
can't be מיפר. mefer. So that's pretty explicit. שמע מינה shema mina
גירושין כהקמה דמי, gerushin kehakamah dami, that sounds like it's a הקמה.
hakamah. אמי הכא בנשואה עסקינן, ami hacha benisua askinan,
now like I told you before that's not a case of an
ארוסה arusa that's a case of a נשואה. nesua. והאי טעמא דאין
יכול להפר משום דאין הבעל מיפר בקודמין. ve-hai ta'ama de-ein yachol lehafer
mishum de-ein habaal mefer bekodmin.
Okay and there he can't do it because he's not מיפר בקודמין
mefer bekodmin and therefore it doesn't prove at all the case of
the ארוסה arusa so we still don't have an answer. By the
way the ר"ן Ran says that what if this case about divorcing
and remarrying, if it was the second marriage was נישואין nisuin then
it would be a problem of אין מיפר בקודמין. ein mefer bekodmin.
What if the first marriage was נישואין, nisuin, he divorced her and
then he remarried her and now he's an ארוס? aras? Could it
work then because an ארוס aras doesn't have a problem of קודמין?
kodmin? But he says no because the first marriage was a נישואין,
nisuin, what did it do? It took her out of her father's
control. Now the second marriage is an אירוסין, erusin, אירוסין erusin without
a father can't do anything. You always need the father. So if
either point was נישואין nisuin it won't work. Either because he's now
an ארוס aras without a father and he can't do anything or
it's a מיפר בקודמין mefer bekodmin because now it's a נישואין. nisuin.
Okay so we don't have an answer whether גירושין gerushin is like
a הקמה hakamah or not but what we do have is raised
the important question about how much is הקמה hakamah like a verbal
act or not a verbal act and what types of things may
or may not constitute a הקמה. hakamah.
Okay so we will stop early again.
I mean I don't want to get too far ahead.